A Finding Aid to the William Christopher Papers, circa 1920s-circa 1973, in the Archives of American Art AAA.chriwill
Archives of American Art
William Christopher papers
circa 1920s-circa 1973
AAA.chriwill
Archives of American Art
7.9 Linear feet
The William Christopher papers measure 7.9 linear feet and date from circa 1920s to circa 1973. Materials include biographical materials, correspondence, writings and notes, five diaries, subject/project files, printed materials, photographs, numerous sketches and eleven sketchbooks, and five unidentified motion picture films. The subject/project files include correspondence, printed materials, and two additional diaries about Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and the 1965 civil rights march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama.
Christopher, William R, 1924-1973
Biographical/Historical note
William Christopher was a painter, art instructor, and Civil Rights activist living and working in New York, New Hampshire, and Vermont. He was born in Columbus, Georgia on March 4, 1924, and served in the U. S. Navy from 1941 to 1943.
Aided by grants and scholarships, Christopher studied in France at the Sorbonne, Academie Julian, and the Ecoles d’Art Americaines between 1946-1948. While there, he also studied with Ossip Zadkine. He returned to New York and studied with Amedee Ozenfant and Hans Hofmann between 1948 and 1950.
Christopher's paintings was greatly influenced by his time spent in Paris and New York, and his later involvement with the Civil Rights movement, Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., and the march in Selma in 1965. His first U. S. solo exhibition was in 1952 at the Roko Gallery in New York, and he exhibited widely in New York, Boston, Washington, D.C. at the Nexus Gallery, the Boston Arts Festival, the Corcoran Gallery of Art, Joan Peterson Gallery, Galeria Juana Mordo, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, among others. In 1964, Christopher was invited to present his paintings to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. during the presentation of Dr. King’s papers to Boston University. This is where Christopher met King.
Christopher moved to Hartland, Vermont in 1960, with his partner painter George Tooker. He remained there for the rest of his life. Christopher died in 1973.
Scope and Contents note
The William Christopher papers measure 7.9 linear feet and date from circa 1920s to circa 1973. Materials include biographical materials, correspondence, writings and notes, five diaries, subject/project files, printed materials, photographs, numerous sketches and eleven sketchbooks, and five unidentified motion picture films. The subject/project files include correspondence, printed materials, and two additional diaries about Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and the 1965 civil rights march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama.
Biographical materials include address books, annotated memorabilia, awards and certificates, curriculum vitae and resume materials, and identification materials. Correspondence is with friends and fellow artists, including actress Osceola Archer and Henry Crapo, galleries, and others. Writings and notes include eleven notebooks, miscellaneous undated notes and papers, annotated drafts and writings by William Christopher, and writings by others. There are five diaries written by William Christopher from the 1940s to the 1960s.
Subject files document miscellaneous projects in which Christopher was involved and/or interested, and include several about Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. containing correspondence, printed material, and two diaries written by Christopher during his attendance of the Civil Rights march from Selma to Montgomery.
Scattered personal business papers concern artwork sold and loaned and personal finances. Printed materials include clippings, exhibition catalogs and materials, magazines and programs, and posters. Photographs are of William Christopher, Henry Crapo, Margaret French, Charles Howard, Bernard Perlin, George Tooker, male models and figures, furniture, landscapes, buildings, and artwork.
Christopher's papers include over one hundred sketches and watercolors, eleven sketchbooks, an artwork by Dimitri Von Mohrenshildt, and one sketch by George Tooker. Also found among the papers are five unidentified film reels made by Christopher for an unfinished project.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
William Christopher donated his papers to the Archives of American Art in 1972.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 10 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1940s-circa 1973 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1947-circa 1973 (1.9 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1947-1970 (0.4 linear feet; Box 3)
Series 4: Diaries, circa 1940s-circa 1960s (0.2 linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1943-1972 (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 4, 9)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, circa 1950-circa 1972 (0.3 linear feet; Box 4)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1950s-circa 1972 (1.4 linear feet; Boxes 4-5, 9, OV12)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1920s-circa 1970s (0.7 linear feet; Boxes 6, 8, MGP 4)
Series 9: Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (1.6 linear feet; Boxes 6-8, OV10-11, 13-18)
Series 10: Unidentified Project, Motion Picture Films, 1961 (0.2 linear feet; Box 7)
Archer, Osceola; Crapo, Henry H.; French, Margaret; Howard, Charles, 1899-1978; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Perlin, Bernard, 1918-; Selma to Montgomery Rights March. (1965 :$cSelma, Ala.); Tooker, George; Von Mohrenschildt, Dimitri Sergius, 1902-2002; African Americans--Civil rights; Civil rights demonstrations--Alabama--Selma; Civil rights--United States; Diaries; Drawings; Motion pictures (visual works); Painters; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, circa 1940s-circa 1973; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes five address books, annotated memorabilia, awards and certificates, curriculum vitae and resume materials, and identification materials, including passport, driver’s licenses, operator’s licenses, birth certificate, and membership cards.
  - Address Book 1, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Book 2, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Loose Material from Address Book 2, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Address Book 3, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Address Book 4, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Address Book 5, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Loose Material from Address Book 5, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annotated Memorabilia, circa 1951-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1947-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Identification Materials and Licenses, 1945-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1947-circa 1973; Series 2; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence includes invitations from friends, fellow artists, and galleries; medical correspondence with doctors after a series of heart attacks; letters from Harold McNeil Robinson, an African American youth who William Christopher helped finance school; correspondence with actress Osceola Archer; and with Henry Crapo, friend and colleague. Additionally, general correspondence includes friends and galleries, such as Margaret Cross, Gaspare D. Cruchi, and many others.
  - Cards and Invitations, circa 1962-circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Envelopes Received, circa 1959-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - Robinson, Harold McNeil, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Crapo, Henry, circa 1950-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Archer, Osceola (Adams), circa 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General, circa 1947-circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - General, circa 1950-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1-25)
  - General, 1968-circa 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1-6)
  - Medical, 1957-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1947-1970; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3
  Writings and notes include eleven notebooks, miscellaneous undated notes and papers, annotated poetry drafts and a story manuscript written by William Christopher. Also included are several writings by others, including an opera manuscript, “Mourning Becomes Electra,” written by Marvin David Levy, and reviews and thesis by Henry H. Crapo.
  - Notebooks 1-4, circa 1947-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notebooks 5-7, circa 1947-1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notebook 8, circa 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notebook 9, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notebook 10, circa 1947-circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notebook 11, circa 1947-1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1947-1970 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
  - Poetry and Story by William Christopher, circa 1940-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Writings By Others, undated, 1960-circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
- Diaries, circa 1940s-circa 1960s; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Five diaries were kept by William Christopher from the 1940s to the 1960s. There are also two additional diaries in the subject files about Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.
  - Diary 1, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Diary 2, 1948-1952 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Diary 3, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Diary 4, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Diary 5, circa 1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Subject Files, 1943-1972; Series 5; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 4, 9
  Subject files are found for miscellaneous projects and the Civil Rights Movement and Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Christopher's files about King include correspondence, printed material, and two diaries Christopher wrote about his attendance of the march from Selma to Montgomery, Alabama. Additional files relate to the Vestris Prize for Choreography, for which Henry Crapo was the sponsor and trustee of the Wasemaquia Charitable Trust Company, and Christopher, George Tooker, and choreographer Stuart Hodes, were judges. Other files relate to a Guggenheim proposed project, Veteran's Adminstration, Galeria Juana Mordo, Vincent Smith, and sculpture by Judith Brown. Files may contain correspondence, printed matter, drafts of writings and ideas, photographs, and clippings.
  - Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., circa 1963-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2-10)
    Oversized materials housed in Box 8.
  - Galeria Juana Mordo, circa 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Guggenheim (Proposed Project), circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - NES Sketch Class, circa 1964 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Sculptures, Judith Brown, circa 1966-crica 1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Vestris Prize for Choreography, circa 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - Veterans Administration, 1943-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Vincent Smith, circa 1968 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Oversized Materials, Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1950-circa 1972; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Box 4
  Scattered personal business records include one account ledger, loan agreements, financial correspondence, invoices and bills paid, receipts, price lists, an apartment lease, and a cursory draft of William Christopher’s will.
  - Account Ledger, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Apartment Lease and Will Draft, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Invoices and Receipts, circa 1952-circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Business Papers, circa 1952-circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
- Printed Material, circa 1950s-circa 1972; Series 7; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 4-5, 9, OV12
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition catalogs and materials, magazines and programs, and posters.
  - Clippings, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 25-29)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 30-34)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1961-circa 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - General Exhibition Materials, circa 1952-circa 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - George Tooker Exhibition Materials, circa 1962-circa 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Printed Material, circa 1950-circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 9-21)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8.
  - Magazines, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 22-25)
  - Programs, circa 1950-circa 1960s (Box 5, Folder 26-28)
  - Oversized General Printed Material, 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Posters, circa 1950s-1972 (Box OV12)
- Photographs, circa 1920s-circa 1970s; Series 8; 0.7 Linear feet Box 6, 8, MGP 4
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged by subject. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers, but listed where they fall intellectually within the collection.
  Photographs include original photographs, negatives, slides, and one glass plate negative. Images depict William Christopher and George Tooker; friends, including Charles Howard, Henry Crapo, Margaret French, and Bernard Perlin; male models and figures; furniture; landscapes and buildings; artwork; and several x-rays of William Christopher’s head and chest.
  - Photographs of William Christopher and Geoge Tooker, circa 1920s-circa 1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of William Christopher, Friends, and Others, circa 1945-circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
    Oversized materials housed in Box 9. 1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 4.
  - Photographs and Negatives of Male Models, 1937-1950 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Photographs of Furniture, circa 1940s-circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Landscapes and Buildings, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Teaching, Models, circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Slides and Photographs of Artwork, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 10-18)
  - X-Rays of William Christopher, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Oversized Photographs of William Christopher, Friends, and Others, circa 1950s-circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Glass Plate Negative, circa 1954-circa 1970; 1 Glass negatives (Box MGP 4)
- Artwork and Sketchbooks, circa 1940s-circa 1970s; Series 9; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 6-8, OV10-11, 13-18
  Artwork and sketchbooks consists of over one hundred sketches and watercolors and eleven sketchbooks. Works by others include a piece by Dimitri Von Mohrenshildt and a sketch by George Tooker. eleven sketchbooks.
  - Paintings, circa 1948-1950 (Box 6, Folder 20-25)
    Oversized material housed in Box 9, OV10-11, 13-18.
  - Artwork by Dimitri von Mohrenshildt, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Sketch by George Tooker, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Sketches, undated, circa 1940s-circa 1953 (Box 6, Folder 28-32)
  - Sketchbook 1, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Sketchbook 2, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Sketchbook 3, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Sketchbooks 4-5, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Sketchbook 6, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook 7, circa 1947 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 8, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 9, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 10, "Dr. King and Lonesome Road", circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook 11, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Paintings and Sketches, circa 1949 (Box 9, Folder 2-5)
  - Oversized Paintings and Sketches, circa 1940s-circa 1970s (Box OV10-11, 13-18)
- Motion Picture Films, circa 1961; Series 10; 0.2 Linear feet Box 7
  Motion picture films consists of five film reels made by William Christopher for an unidentified and unfinished project.
  - Unidentified Film Reels, circa 1961; 5 Film reels 16 mm, 100 feet (Box 7, Folder 7-9, Item 1-5)